A Guide to the John W. Daniel Papers, 1888-1910
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
John W. Daniel Papers, 1888-1910
The Library of Virginia
21623
21 leaves and 2 pages
John W. Daniel
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Glenna Whybrew, Lynchburg, Virginia, 9 October 1939.
Biographical Information
John Warwick Daniel was born 5 September 1842 in Lynchburg, Virginia, to William Daniel, Jr. (1806-1873) and Sarah Ann Warwick Daniel (d. 1845). Daniel attended Lynchburg College and Locust Grove Academy, but left school when the Civil War began. Commissioned a lieutenant, he rose to the rank of major and received a crippling wound at the Battle of the Wilderness. After the Civil War, Daniel began practicing law and entered politics. He served in the House of Delegates from 1869 to 1871 and in the state Senate from 1875 to 1881. Daniel was elected to the United States Senate by the Virginia General Assembly in 1885 and served from 1887 until his death. He represented Lynchburg in the 1901-1902 state constitutional convention, and was considered a potential vice-presidential nominee at the 1904 Democratic National Convention. Daniel married Julia Elizabeth Murrell (1850-1937) 24 November 1869. He died 29 June 1910. Sarah Warwick Halsey (1845-1918) was Daniel's sister.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1888-1910, of John Warwick Daniel (1842-1910) of Lynchburg, Virginia, and United States Senator, consisting of correspondence to Daniel concerning the State Normal School; the gold standard and Daniel's pro-silver stance; Daniel as a possible presidential candidate in 1896, including a clipping and a poem; the 1904 Democratic National Convention; copyright legislation; anti-tariff laws and labor; Daniel's health; and Daniel's election as vice president of the Virginia League for International Arbitration. Papers also include a pass, 1900, for the Seaboard Air Line Railway; circular letter, 7 June 1909, from Daniel to his constituents reviewing the congressional session; resolutions, n.d., of the John Daniel Democratic Club of Botetourt County, Virginia, supporting Daniel and opposing William Mahone (1826-1895); and a note from C.A.B. containing a clipping on the 1892 Democratic National Convention.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
John W. Daniel Papers, 1898-1904 (LVA accession 21589).
John W. Daniel Papers, 1887-1910 (LVA accession 21636).
John W. Daniel Papers, 1893-1910 (LVA accession 21683).
John W. Daniel Papers, 1874-1914 (LVA accession 23923).
John W. Daniel Letter, 18 July 1904 (LVA accession 27993).
Contents List
- Letter, 4 August 1888, from John L. Buchanan (1831-1922) of Richmond, Virginia, to Daniel discussing the relationship between Sarah Warwick Halsey (1845-1918) of Culpeper, Virginia, and the State Normal School.
- Letter, 26 December 1888, from Buchanan to Halsey about the next meeting of the Board of Visitors for the State Normal School.
- Letter, 1 February 1895, from Mills Lee Eure, Norfolk, Virginia, to Daniel critizing President Grover Cleveland's message on the gold standard.
- Letter, 2 February 1895, from Henry Lee Staples (ca. 1842-1897), Richmond, to Daniel supporting Daniel's pro-silver position.
- Letter, 7 June 1896, from Leo P. Wheat,of Bedford County, Virginia, but then in Atlanta, Georgia, sending a clipping from the Atlanta Constitution urging Daniel's nomination for president and a poem.
- Pass, 30 May-5 June 1900, for the Seaboard Air Line Railway from John Skelton Williams (1865-1926) to Daniel.
- Letter, 15 July 1904, from Scott Nesbit, Warrenton, Virginia, to Daniel congratulating him on his work at the recent Democratic National Convention held in St. Louis, Missouri.
- Letter, 12 March 1905, from William Lawrence Royall (1845-1912), Richmond, to Daniel commenting on an article forwarded to Daniel.
- Letter, 29 December 1906, from William Henry Sargeant (1842-1917), Norfolk, to Daniel asking Daniel to oppose the "copyright bill."
- Circular letter, 7 June 1909, from Daniel reviewing event and legislation in the United States Congress.
- Letter, 20 May 1910, from Harvey Lee Harwood (1861-1936), Richmond, to Daniel expressing wishes for Daniel's recovery.
- Letter, 9 June 1910, from Wesley Setzler to Daniel concerning anti-trust laws and labor.
- Letter, 15 June 1910, from Philip Edward Williamson Goodwin (1875-1956) informing Daniel of his election as vice-president of the Virginia League for International Arbitration.
- Resolutions, no date, of the John Daniel Democratic Club of Botetourt County, Virginia, in support of Daniel and in opposition to William Mahone (1826-1895).
- Note, no date, from C.A.B. to Daniel which includes a newspaper clipping on the 1892 Democratic Convention.